So, here's the thing.
We have a region name.
We have the Pokedex.
This all looks pretty good,
except if we take a look at this actually,
and let's say we wanted to change the region name.
This is actually pretty common.
So let's say we want to say let's do an H2,
and this is a region name.
There we go. We see Konto here,
and actually let me, there you go.
Now, it's not being clicked.
So if you want to change this,
you might be thinking, well, okay,
I know what I'm going to do.
I'm going to say inside of,
we'll create a method here just to make things very clear.
That says, change region name,
and then this.regionname is going to be equal to Hoenn after this.
All right. Then what we're going to do is we're going to create a button.
Actually, no, that's going to be at the bottom of a very long list.
Equals change region name,
and then change region name, save.
So far, again, just to recap,
we want to be able to change the region name.
So we created a button that runs
this function that should,
as we've been practicing already,
just change Konto to Hoenn.
So we say that and click.
You'll notice that nothing is happening.
This might feel weird because after all,
isn't this what we've been doing this entire time?
The secret to this lies in the fact
that what we talked about when we covered setup,
which is that everything in here is vanilla JavaScript.
So what you're returning here,
while view will go ahead and register it to the rest of the component,
there's no reactivity attached to it right now.
Because why? It's a plain JavaScript const.
It's a constant, and the same thing is happening with Pokedex.
In other words, all the stuff that we were talking about regarding
reactive data, computer properties,
that will not work with this because at this point,
it's not reactive.
So how do we bring some reactivity?
Well, the way we do that is actually by using view helper methods.
So we mentioned that earlier,
where a really popular thing now with view3 is the ability to parse out
different functions to help people use it in different contexts.
Well, there is a helper method
for turning something into a reactive reference.
The way we do that is we import from view,
and we destructure out this method called ref.
Again, if you think of ref, think of reactive reference.
So how does that work? Well, what we do is,
we actually just wrap the value that we want to be
reactive inside of this helper method.
That's what we do.
So now if I refresh this and we change it,
you'll notice it's now actually being tracked by view.
So this ref and a lot of the concepts we'll be talking about,
is actually really critical because going forward,
whenever you're working inside of composition API,
you have to be very explicit about when you want view to introduce magic.
So this is actually one of the things I do think that's beneficial to
the composition API is because now,
you know exactly where view is coming in to do things.
Whereas in the options API,
you could argue that the this context could be
confusing for JavaScript developers and what if they
wanted to come in and change some stuff, right?
Composition API is your ability to get at the primitives and say,
okay, this is the stuff I want to do,
and then view, do your magic for this kind of stuff.
So for example, if we wanted to say,
let's actually have ability to have like an all caps region name.
Well, the way we could easily do that is you can have a computer property.
That's how I would approach this.
So we'll say region all caps and
actually I'll just be more specific region name all caps.
And what do we need how?
We need a computer property and guess what?
The helper method is computed.
So we have a computer property, but what we need to do inside of our computer
property is we need to run a function.
Because if we look back at our other apps that use computed,
let's go back into another component that uses it.
You'll see that all of our computer properties actually are functions,
which makes sense because they need to run a computation on the things that are
the dependencies.
So we have an arrow function in here and what are we going to do?
We're going to go ahead and we're going to return just like we did before.
We're going to turn the region name to uppercase.
This is probably our first instinct as far as how we would make this work.
And so to make sure this works,
we got to make sure we return this to region name all caps just like that.
And then let's go ahead and expose that here as an H3.
Region name all caps just like that and we'll save.
And you might notice that, well, something's broken.
What's going on?
Well, it's saying region name by two uppercase is not a function.
You might be thinking, this is weird, but region name is a string, right?
It's not.
Yeah, it's not a string anymore.
It is now a reactive reference, which actually some of you have noticed when
you're doing the inspecting of the element.
Let's go ahead and actually log region name at this point and see what we get.
If I refresh that, that's fine, we get a massive error.
And you'll see things like the ref implementation.
You also might have seen as well when you're doing the options API,
you saw proxies show up when you would log out of value.
And I know that was confusing at first to some people because they're
expecting to just see what the value actually is.
But one of the big rewrites of view three when it came to the reactivity engine
is that it's using the JavaScript proxies underneath in order to manage how
all the dependencies are being tracked.
And so again, you don't need to understand how proxies work for
you to be familiar with or basically to work with view.
But in case that's something you're interested in, I just wanted to give you
sort of like a little bit of a preview of that so
that you can always dive into that if you want to learn more about that.
But you'll notice here that once again, region name is not a string.
What is it?
It's a ref implementation because it's a reactive reference.
Meaning the way we actually get to the value of it is actually to basically
think of it as an object now.
It's an object that has the ability to update it, it's dependencies.
And so when we actually want to access the raw value of a reference,
we have to actually unpack the thing.
The way we do that is by saying dot value.
And you'll notice once you do that, everything works.
Now, this might feel a little bit odd after using the options API for
a little while because after all in the past, or actually not even in the past,
if we wanted to, we could have theoretically created a computer property at this level.
And just for the sake of having comparison, this will be region name lowercase.
And so what we would do here is return this.regionname.to lowercase.
Just like that.
And then we'll just add another h3.regionname all.
Okay, no, no, it looks like it's just lowercase, yeah.
Okay, save.
Okay, so that happens to work.
Let me have a differentiator here.
There we go.
Okay, sentence case, all case, okay.
So you might be thinking, well, this is way nicer, right?
Like why do I want dot value?
And I'll say when I first was exposed to this, I would agree.
It definitely feels odd.
But there is something to understand about the reason why this is actually
helpful is because we do have to remember that when you're working in vanilla
JavaScript, it is important to be able to tell when something is viewed,
when something is not.
And so we think about const region name.
The fact that you actually have to unpack the value does signify to people that
when they're working with this particular value,
that it's already attached to the view reactivity.
That said, I wanted to give you the pros of how people see that because
a lot of people do like ref.
But in the event you're like, I really don't like ref.
What you can do instead is you can do this helper method called reactive.
And so what reactive is, is basically think of the data option from
the options API packaged in a nice little helper function.
Because earlier, there was a question regarding around the fact that,
what if I don't like the name data?
What if I want to call it state?
Well, we can.
In this case, state, it's a reactive object.
And inside of here, let's just say, I'll just do like region two.
And I actually don't know a third region.
It's fine, okay, I'll just do element type and let's say lightning.
Okay, so when you're doing the state, first of all,
I'll go ahead and log out state.
Once you end up getting is something that looks like a lot more of what people
are probably expecting when they're actually inspecting element,
which is the proxy.
This is what we've seen earlier when we actually inspected the options API
element in that you have to look at the target in order to get underneath it.
But what's nice about this now is that, again, this is gonna be misplaced.
But if we do state.element type.to uppercase and run it,
you'll see it actually just works.
And so the way to think of reactive is it's like a nicely packaged way of
collecting your refs together and that you don't have to unpackage it with dot value.
And so there are plenty of code bases I've seen that people never touch ref.
They like reactive, because reactive feels like options API,
but you're in the composition API setting.
And so is there a right or wrong way to do this?
Absolutely not.
So for the sake of having this example also be here,
I'm just gonna say element type all caps.
And then we'll make sure to return this here, make it alphabetical.
And then I'll just make sure it's here and then we should be good, okay?
So there we have it.
This is the fundamentals around composition API.
As far as the highlights to consider for this once again,
is that you're now in free form JavaScript land.
So this is where I would say comparing options API to composition API is that
options API, you don't need as much JavaScript to get up and running, I would argue.
And I've seen that before with people who have just enough to understand the syntax,
where because of the this syntax, they were able to just kind of get in there,
make some changes, make some swaps.
And the templating was easy enough that people without a lot of JavaScript
experience could actually be productive on a code base.
With something like this, however, when it comes to the composition API,
as you can see, there's a lot more going on.
You need to understand helper functions, you need to know about modules,
you need to go ahead and make sure you know if you're using ref that it's a dot
value that the skill cap jumps considerably when it comes to the amount of
JavaScript you need to know in order to be productive with composition API.